Good afternoon. Today's דף Daf is דף ד' Daf Daled and we
pick up at the bottom of ג' עמוד ב' Gimel Amud Bet
and what we're in the middle of discussing is, you know, the
משנה Mishnah
allows
for overrides of the prohibition of חול המועד Chol HaMoed and of
שמיטה Shmita of watering the field. So חול המועד Chol HaMoed is
understandable. I mean, at least the way the גמרא Gemara is now
phrasing it, it makes it sound like it's all דרבנן De-rabbanan anyway
and it's not even about מלאכה, Melacha, it's about טרחא. Tircha. So
we can override the מקום הפסד. Mekom Hefsed. What's the story about
שמיטה? Shmita? Two basic answers: one is שמיטה Shmita nowadays is דרבנן;
De-rabbanan; the other is that even at the דאורייתא De-oraita level, not
all of the מלאכות, Melachos, only a small number of מלאכות Melachos
are actually biblical, only אבות Avos not תולדות. Tolados. So those are
basically the explanations about that.
Then relatedly, we got this teaching from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that
said תוספת Tosefet isn't forbidden, that תוספת Tosefet of שביעית... Shevi'is... what's...
or it's not that it's not forbidden, you don't get lashes. What's
the איסור Issur of תוספת? Tosefet? One explanation was it was חרישה,
Charisha, plowing, which would have been therefore one of those things that
would have been seen as a תולדה, Tolada, not an אב, Av,
not mentioned explicitly in the פסוק. Pasuk. And the other explanation is
we're talking about the period before שמיטה, Shmita, before ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, that gets added on, which is like some of the first
משניות Mishnayos in שביעית Shevi'is discuss this whole period of the adding
on, all the way from פסח Pesach and from שבועות, Shavuos, not
doing work on the field that is going to be for preparing
it for the coming year, as opposed to doing work that is
for being good for the fruit for the current year. And that's
a whole series of משניות, Mishnayos, this period of תוספת שביעית, Tosefet
Shevi'is, and therefore the teaching is, is that even though there is
this aspect of תוספת שביעית, Tosefet Shevi'is, you don't get lashes for
it. Now, where... so that raises the question of what is its
nature, what is its weight? So we have this משנה Mishnah that
basically speaks about the different periods and then רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
who overrode it. So that certainly makes it sound like it's דרבנן.
De-rabbanan. Even within that the גמרא Gemara said, "How could he override
if it's a תקנה? Takkanah? A later בית דין Beis Din can't
override an earlier תקנה." Takkanah. And it gives the answer, might I
say, a very convenient answer, that this was already stipulated that it
could be overridden in the later if needed, which at least, you
know, we can understand to the degree that that's... that this could
create a lot of sort of onerous type of a demand, so
therefore, you know, in terms of an effect on the economy and
so on, so therefore they allowed that to be overridden. Fine. But
anyway, that situates it as a דרבנן. De-rabbanan. But then we've got
a problem because there's evidence that it is a הלכה למשה מסיני,
Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai, not a דאורייתא De-oraita by the פסוק, Pasuk,
but going back to the origins of the תורה, Torah, הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai, and that's based on the fact that there's
a special הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai that if you have
these ten saplings, עשרה נטיעות, Asara Netiot, planted in a certain space,
you can work it up to ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Which basically
means if you need a הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai to
say you can work it up to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, means
that the implication is that for everything else it's forbidden. You know,
you can't go up to the last minute. So from there you
see the הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai we can infer already
there's an idea of תוספת. Tosefet. It's not just a דרבנן. De-rabbanan.
So the last answer we've had in the גמרא Gemara is fine,
the הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai is thirty days before ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah and that's inviolate, except for the one thing the
הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai itself allows, the case of the
ten trees, and then the... then from more than thirty days before,
going all the way back to שבועות Shavuos or פסח, Pesach, that
is purely דרבנן, De-rabbanan, and that's what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and
his בית דין Beis Din overrode. So we have two sections now
of תוספת שביעית: Tosefet Shevi'is: the part that's biblical or whatever הלכה
למשה מסיני, Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai, the month before, and then the part
that's even earlier that's דרבנן. De-rabbanan. But the גמרא Gemara is not
done and now it wants to argue that it's actually biblical. So
we pick up at the bottom of ג' עמוד ב'. Gimel Amud
Bet. Yes.
This is unique in ש"ס, Shas, this idea of retroactively activating a
דאורייתא De-oraita
and a בית דין Beis Din making a תקנה Takkanah and building
in the fact that their תקנה Takkanah can be overridden. I mean...
Right, so that's... so you know the idea of... of... I didn't
understand the point about retroactively activating a דאורייתא, De-oraita, but in terms
of whether דאורייתא De-oraita or דרבנן De-rabbanan have the right...
תוספת שביעית... Tosefet Shevi'is...
no, I mean the simple sense is that somebody...
You mean it was already in place but it didn't have to
be activated yet?
You mean the הלכה למשה מסיני? Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai? Yes. Well, the
way the גמרא Gemara is figuring it, I mean I would say
the פשט Pshat is that it's all דרבנן. De-rabbanan. That's the פשט
Pshat of the evidence. You know, the גמרא Gemara based on this
case of this הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai of עשרה נטיעות,
Asara Netiot, which is one מאן דאמר, Man Da-amar, one statement of
one person, the גמרא Gemara creates a hybrid type of a situation.
So his, you know, what it actually was is unclear, but that's
the way the גמרא Gemara is constructing it. But the idea that
the גמרא Gemara is saying that this was initially stipulated to allow
it to be overridden, yes, that's pretty rare. I'm not... I can't
recall if the גמרא Gemara ever explicitly says, you know, that somewhere
else as well, but you know there is a problem because on
the one hand you've got this principle you don't override, on the
other hand we found that there are cases of override. You have
that at the beginning of... where do you get this as well?
The whole case in עבודה זרה Avoda Zara about certain תקנות Takkanos
about the oil of the non-Jew and the, you know, other types
of prohibitions about various products of non-Jews that it says that רבי
יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi and his בית דין Beis Din overrode
it and so on. So then the גמרא Gemara tries and I
think in the beginning of ביצה Beitzah the גמרא Gemara deals with
overriding תקנות. Takkanos. So the גמרא Gemara tries to navigate its way
through the fact that those תקנות Takkanos were overridden based on the
principle they're not supposed to be.
Yeah I'm just trying to understand a little bit more about ביטול
חמץ Bitul Chametz insofar as we understand it as it was discussed
in the סוגיא sugya or organized it down whatever it is. So
this הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai, is there no like book
of this?
It's just sort of... Well, there's no book of the other stuff
also, it's all oral. But I will say about הלכה למשה מסיני
Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai is that for רמב״ם, Rambam, you know, רמב״ם Rambam
had to deal with the challenge about, thank you so much, רמב״ם
Rambam had to deal with a challenge about if, you know, the
Karaites critiqued that if this is all, you think you have the
מסורה, Mesora, how could you think you have the מסורה? Mesora? Every
single page of גמרא Gemara has twenty debates. So clearly you guys,
whatever tradition you had, got completely lost, so you can't trust the
tradition altogether. And the רמב״ם's Rambam basic response to that was that
the debates in the גמרא Gemara are not based on a corruption
of the transmission. These are things that were never initially transmitted. It
was always that the text was given for the rabbis
to figure out for themselves what it meant. So the debates are
coming from different interpretations, not from different traditions. He said the one
exception to this is the one thing the גמרא Gemara labels as
a tradition is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai. And therefore the
רמב״ם Rambam made the claim that the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe
MiSinai in the גמרא Gemara were never debated. Those were transmissions and
therefore they were always purely transmitted, never debated. Of course, that's not
true, הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai are debated as well. Okay,
so anyway, but let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like והני הלכתא נינהו Ve-hanei hilchata
ninhu five lines from the bottom on ג עמוד ב. Gimmel Amud
Bet. והני הלכתא נינהו? Ve-hanei hilchata ninhu? Are these הלכה למשה מסיני?
Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai? Now you've created this hybrid of part הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai, part דרבנן. de-Rabbanan. But now the גמרא Gemara
is going to push it further. Is it really just a הלכה
למשה מסיני? Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai? קראי נינהו, Krai ninhu, it's a verse!
How do you know? דתנן, de-tenan,
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, or דתניא de-tanya as a question,
is it משנה ברייתא? Mishnah Baraita? Anyway, בחריש ובקציר תשבת. Be-charish u-va-katzir
tishbot.
You shall rest in the plowing and in the harvesting, a פסוק
pasuk that in the simple sense talks about שבת, Shabbos, but רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר, omer, אין צריך לומר חריש וקציר של שביעית,
ein tzarich lomar charish ve-katzir shel shevi'it, שהרי כבר נאמר שדך לא
תזרע וכרמך לא תזמור. she-harei kvar ne'emar sadecha lo tizra ve-charmecha lo
tizmor.
So immediately we assume it's not talking about שבת, Shabbos, it's talking
about שמיטה Shmita because why? Because it's too specific to שבת. Shabbos.
If it was שבת, Shabbos, it would just say don't do מלאכה
melacha on שבת. Shabbos. Why would it be that specific?
So therefore the first assumption is it's talking about שמיטה. Shmita. But
therefore it can't be talking just about שמיטה Shmita because we already
know you can't do this stuff on שמיטה. Shmita. It says don't
plant and
don't prune. Of course the problem is it doesn't mention חרישה, charisha,
and we just got through a whole דף daf yesterday where חרישה
charisha was being seriously questioned whether it was biblical or not because
maybe the תורה Torah didn't forbid the תולדות. toldot. But whatever, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva assumes that somehow we would have already known חרישה,
charisha, going back to yesterday's discussion. So therefore this doesn't have to
forbid the stuff on שמיטה Shmita itself. אלא, Ela, so what is
it forbidding? חריש של ערב שביעית שנכנס לשביעית, Charish shel erev shevi'it
she-nichnas le-shevi'it, ד עמוד א, Dalet Amud Aleph,
the plowing that occurs before שמיטה Shmita because you do some plowing
before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah to get the ground ready. Right, you
know, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is the beginning of the planting season,
so you could do some plowing before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. וקציר
של שביעית שיוצא למוצאי שביעית, Ve-katzir shel shevi'it she-yotzei le-motza'ei shevi'it, harvesting
that's going after, you know, the end of the שמיטה. Shmita. And
that would be a little bit funny that it would be the
end of אלול Elul and there would still be stuff you hadn't
harvested, but maybe, I mean particularly I guess if you're talking about
fruit, it's possible. So therefore what the תורה Torah is telling you
is don't just do the תשבות tishbot on שמיטה Shmita itself, have
it extend before and after. There's a biblical idea of תוספת שביעית.
Tosefet Shevi'it. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael אומר, omer, מה חריש רשות אף קציר רשות. mah charish reshut
af katzir reshut. No, it's telling you something completely different. It's telling
you that it's talking about שבת, Shabbos, like פשט peshat of the
פסוק, pasuk, and it's telling you חריש charish is forbidden and קציר
katzir is forbidden on שבת. Shabbos. Why did it point those out?
To tell you the following things. The same way there's never a
מצוה mitzvah to do חרישה charisha and it's forbidden on שבת, Shabbos,
therefore the type of קצירה, ketzira, harvest, that's forbidden on שבת Shabbos
is harvesting that is a non-מצוה mitzvah harvest. What does that exclude?
יצא קציר העומר שהיא מצוה, Yatza katzir ha-omer she-hi mitzvah, which excludes
harvesting for the עומר, Omer, which is a מצוה mitzvah to harvest
the עומר Omer itself and therefore on that day. And therefore that
can be done even on שבת. Shabbos. So that's why it pointed
out those two, to tell you that when there's a case of
a מצוה mitzvah to do the harvesting, it can be done on
שבת. Shabbos. So we answered our question? No, we didn't, well, we
didn't answer our question. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's biblical. So
what do you do about the earlier evidence, to answer your question
about isn't it talking about שבת? Shabbos? The גמרא Gemara didn't answer
its question, which is we had earlier evidence that it's rabbinic or
הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai, and here we have רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva saying it's biblical. So what do you do with that?
Do you think
like רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, right? Well, that's an option, but let's
take a look. אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Ela amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, כי גמירי הלכתא למשרי ילדה קראי למאסר זקינה. ki
gemiri hilchata le-mishrei yalda krai le-me'esar zekeina.
Here's the way it works. The פסוקים pesukim introduce the idea of
the prohibition of תוספת שביעית Tosefet Shevi'it or the obligation of תוספת
שביעית. Tosefet Shevi'it. So therefore based on the פסוקים, pesukim, you know
that there's a period, let's again say a month, there's a period
before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah that it's additionally forbidden. to do שמיטה.
Shemittah. That's what the פסוקים Pesukim tell you. Comes along the הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai and tells you that there's an exception
to this rule. The exception is the saplings, the ten saplings in
a particular area. So it's true, if I just had the הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai and told me the exception, I could
have inferred if there's an exception, I can infer that there's a
rule prohibiting it. But actually, the rule prohibiting it comes from the
biblical verse, the exception comes from the הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe
Misinai, and then the דרבנן DeRabbanan comes from the period before a
month before. So we have a tripartite sort of structure there. Okay.
So whatever,
the פסוק Pasuk is talking about two different things. Okay. כי גמיר
הלכתא למשרי ילדה קרא למעשה זקנה. Ki gemir hilchesa lemishrei yaldah kra
lemeise zekeina.
So now the גמרא Gemara isn't happy with this answer. וכיון דהלכתא
למשרי ילדה למה זקנה לאו ממילא זקנה אסירה? Vecheivan dehilchesa lemishrei yaldah
lamah zekeina lav mimeila zekeina asira?
No, it's superfluous. If you have a הלכה Halacha that gives you
an exception by the case of the saplings, I could have inferred
that everything else, old trees, everything else is forbidden. So you still
wouldn't need a פסוק. Pasuk. Although, you know, the answer seems like
reasonable. Why not have a prohibition based on a פסוק Pasuk and
an exception based on a הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha Lemoshe Misinai? But
the גמרא Gemara is saying, no, the פסוק Pasuk would still be
superfluous. אלא Ella here's the way it works, like Michael said: הלכתא
לרבי ישמעאל קרא לרבי עקיבא. Hilchesa le-Rabbi Yishmael kra le-Rabbi Akiva.
Going back to the רמב"ם's Rambam claim that הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
Lemoshe Misinais are not debated, the גמרא Gemara says actually it's a
debate whether you need the הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. According
to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, he does not have a verse for
the idea of תוספת, Tosafos, he learns it to talk about the
עומר. Omer. So according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, תוספת Tosafos is
inferred from this הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai about the saplings.
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, who's got a verse for the idea of
תוספת, Tosafos, בחריש ובקציר תשבות, Becharish uvekatzir tishbos, does not have this
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Misinai and therefore it's not superfluous, therefore
he bases it on a verse. Okay. So what do we have
now? What's the nature of תוספת שביעית? Tosafos Shevi'is? We have a
section of clearly דרבנן, DeRabbanan, בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beis Hillel u-Beis
Shammai, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel overrode it. We're saying that's more than
a month before, that's goes back to פסח Pesach or to שבועות.
Shavuos. We have the period of a month before. Is that biblical,
is it based on a verse or is it a הלכה למשה
מסיני? Halacha Lemoshe Misinai? We're saying it's a debate. רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva got a verse for תוספת שביעית, Tosafos Shevi'is, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael does not, so he would base it on the הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai, which would mean that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
wouldn't hold of the exception of the ten trees. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רבי יוחנן אמר רבן גמליאל ובית דינו
מדאורייתא בטלוה. Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabban Gamliel uveit dino mide'oraisa bitloha. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, because I've already tried to
continue with this...
I'm sorry, that wasn't a... that was a... רבן גמליאל ובית... רבי
יוחנן אמר רבן גמליאל ובית דינו מדאורייתא בטלוה. Rabban Gamliel uveit... Rabbi
Yochanan amar Rabban Gamliel uveit dino mide'oraisa bitloha. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan in the name of רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, when they nullified
it, as opposed to before that we said this whole structure that
there's a section that's דרבנן DeRabbanan and that דרבנן DeRabbanan section is
being overridden, the גמרא Gemara is now framing it as no, actually
their ability to override the law of תוספת Tosafos was found support
in a biblical verse. What support did they find when they were
coming to nullify the idea of תוספת? Tosafos? So מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? גמר שבת שבת משבת בראשית. Gemar Shabbos Shabbos miShabbos Bereishis. They
made a comparison to, you know, normal שבת. Shabbos. So it's all
about תשבות. tishbos. So מה להלן היא אסורה לפניה ולאחריה מותרים. Mah
lehallan hi asira lefaneha ule'achareha muttarim. The same way by a normal
שבת Shabbos there's only the idea of שבת Shabbos itself, you before
and after is totally permissible. אף כאן היא אסורה לפניה ולאחריה מותרים.
Af kan hi asira lefaneha ule'achareha muttarim. Even here too, only it
is forbidden, immediate before and immediately after is permissible.
Michael says, what do you mean, we do have תוספת שבת? Tosafos
Shabbos? Okay, but תוספת שבת Tosafos Shabbos is a few minutes, it's
nothing like six months before. So you look in תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות
Tosafos says מה להלן היא אסורה לפניה ולאחריה מותרים. Mah lehallan hi
asira lefaneha ule'achareha muttarim. וקשה, Ve-kasheh, if you ask, והא נפקא לן
מקרא במסכת יומא פרק בתרא דצריך לעשות תוספת גבי שבת בין בכניסתה
בין ביציאתה להוסיף מחול על הקודש. ve-ha nafka lan mikra be-maseches Yoma
perek basra de-tzarich la'asos tosafos gabbei Shabbos bein be-chnisasa bein be-ytzi'asa lehosif
me-chol al ha-kodesh. There's an idea of adding a little bit before
שבת Shabbos begins and after it gets out. איכא למימר Ika leimeimar
הוא פורתא לא קחשיב. hu purta lo kachashiv. That's a tiny bit,
we're not considering that. כיון דלא הוי אלא כל שהוא, Keivan delo
havei ella kol shehu, it's a tiny bit, and you say a
tiny bit just don't cut it to the last minute. That's the
idea. וכי ההיא שיעורא, Ve-ki ha-hi shi'ura, that's because you think that's
the פשט, pshat, נמי מודי רבן גמליאל דצריך להוסיף. nami modei Rabban
Gamliel de-tzarich lehosif. And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel wouldn't deny you want
to add a minute, an hour, so you don't go into שמיטה
Shemittah ten... to working the land to the last second. Fine, but
that's an issue conceptually, that's about being careful not to overstep the
line. Don't wait till the very last second, you might miss that
exact minute, that exact second you might overstep the line. That's what
תוספת Tosafos is. Not that there's an actual value of having a
significant amount of observance begin prior. That's only something that you get
by שמיטה, Shemittah, and therefore he says רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and
their בית דין Beis Din said you're trying to say this is
biblical, I dispute your interpretation of the פסוק, Pasuk, or maybe even
I dispute your הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. I don't think
it's biblical, I dispute your interpretation of the פסוק, Pasuk, and therefore
I do away with the whole thing. It does not fit, interesting,
not because I've got another פסוק, Pasuk, but because since the תורה
Torah identifies it as שבת, Shabbat, it's got to fit that model
of שבת. Shabbat. Again, this is a very interesting... Interesting, now because
I've got another פסוק, pasuk, but that since the תורה Torah identifies
it as שבת, Shabbat, it's got to fit that model of שבת.
Shabbat. Again, this is a very interesting thing, tying back to a
point I made yesterday, how much do we think about שמיטה shmita
in terms of שבת? Shabbat? You know, often that's the question at
the טעמי המצוות ta'amei hamitzvos level, right? Like, is the purpose of
שמיטה shmita to provide for the poor, you know, in like a
social justice, or is the purpose of שמיטה shmita a type of
a שבת Shabbat to show כי לי כל הארץ ki li kol
ha'aretz and you don't work the land seven years, you work it
six years, you recognize it belongs to God, it's a type of
a שבת Shabbat of the land. By the way, that's reflected in
the different words for שמיטה, shmita, right? Is שמיטה, shmita, right, שביעית,
shevi'it, right? Or is שמיטה, shmita, שמיטה? shmita? שמיטה, shmita, שמיטה shmita
means שמוט, shamot, to release. And when the verses use the, in
בהר, Behar, they don't use the word שמיטה, shmita, they just use
the word תשבות tishbos and שביעית shevi'it and שבת. Shabbat. And there,
there's very little emphasis on providing for the poor. Other places in
the תורה, Torah, in שמות Shmot and דברים, Devarim, the תורה Torah
uses the word תשמוט. tishmot. And there, when it uses the word
שמוט, shamot, שמוט, shamot,
and שמיטה, shmita, the emphasis is releasing of debts, providing for the
poor. Exactly. So there are two different concepts. So sometimes that's raised
at the טעמי המצוות ta'amei hamitzvos level, but also halachically, how much
do aspects of שמיטה shmita are patterned after שבת? Shabbat? So we've
now seen two discussions. One is אבות ותולדות, avot and toldot, which
you could have said אבות avot just means the verses by שמיטה
shmita itself, but רש"י Rashi says אבות avot means a subset of
what we learn by שבת Shabbat from the משכן, Mishkan, he invokes
the משכן, Mishkan, okay, and the שבת Shabbat concept. And here, רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is saying, I don't care if you've got a
פסוק pasuk בחריש ובקציר becharish u-vakatizir or you've got a הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, I don't buy that interpretation, that's not consistent
with this concept of as שבת, Shabbat, okay? And therefore they were
able to reject the whole idea of תוספת. tosefet. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues like this.
And also overrule...
Right, so that's the question. At this stage, is the גמרא Gemara
continuing to think there's two stages, a דאורייתא de'oraisa and a דרבנן,
derabbanan, and then רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין beis
din did away with everything? Or maybe at this stage the גמרא
Gemara is thinking that for those that it's דאורייתא de'oraisa or הלכה
למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, it's all דאורייתא, de'oraisa, there's no two
stages, and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and בית דינו beis dino just
did away with the whole thing. Okay, so it's a little bit
not clear at this stage because the גמרא Gemara is still buying
into the two, you know, the hybrid nature of it. Okay, let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara continues. מתקיף לה רב אשי. Matkif
lei Rav Ashi. רב אשי Rav Ashi asked: מן דאמר הלכה, man
de-amar halacha, אתי גזירה שוה עקרא הלכתא? asi gezeira shava akra hilchasa?
So he doesn't like this idea, that just because you think it's
like a שבת, Shabbat, that can override a specific derivation of the
verse. Right, I don't care if you think it's הלכה למשה מסיני,
halacha lemoshe misinai, your fact that you say "oh, it's like שבת"
Shabbat is going to let you reject the הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha
lemoshe misinai? ומן דאמר קרא, ve-man de-amar kera, אתי גזירה שוה עקרא
קרא? asi gezeira shava akra kera? And if it's a verse, גזירה
שוה gezeira shava is going to come and uproot a verse? Now
that's a funny question. It's one thing if I have a specific
tradition, it actually tells me there's an idea of תוספת. tosefet. But
if it's a question of how to read a verse, why can't
I use the גזירה שוה gezeira shava to direct me to read
the verse in a particular way? So I don't know exactly what
the question is, but let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
גמרא Gemara says: I don't buy it, just because it's called שבת,
Shabbat, that's going to override these דרשות? drashos? אלא אמר רב אשי:
ela amar Rav Ashi: רבן גמליאל ובית דינו סברו כרבי ישמעאל, Rabban
Gamliel ve-veis dino savru ke-Rabbi Yishmael, דאמר הלכתא גמירי לה. de-amar hilchasa
gemiri lah. Now, here's the only way to explain how they could
reject it. And again, they're really trying to understand that they rejected
the whole thing, not this hybrid level of a דאורייתא de'oraisa and
דרבנן. derabbanan. Maybe it's all דאורייתא, de'oraisa, and even though it's all
דאורייתא, de'oraisa, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel rejected it. How do you reject
it? Because they hold it's a הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai,
וכי גמירי הלכתא בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, ve-ki gemiri hilchasa bizman shebeish
hamikdash kayam, דומיא דניסוך המים, dumya de-nisuch hamayim, אבל בזמן שאין בית
המקדש קיים, aval bizman she'ein beis hamikdash kayam, לא. lo. Maybe they
felt that rather than interpret the verse, you interpret the הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, that the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha lemoshe misinai
only applies when there is a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now, why
would you say such a thing? Because this הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
lemoshe misinai that's transmitted about these ten trees is always transmitted in
a group of three: ניסוך המים, Nisuch HaMayim, ערבה, Arava,
and עשר נטיעות.
Eser Netiyot. So therefore, the two, ניסוך המים Nisuch HaMayim and ערבה,
Arava, are מקדש Mikdash related. It's not the ערבה Arava we do
with the banging, it's the walking around the מזבח Mizbe'ach they do
with the ערבה. Arava. So maybe the עשר נטיעות Eser Netiyot is
also when there is a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And what's the
relevance of בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to שמיטה? shmita? You know, the
more immediate relevance to this is there's no בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
presumably that means that there's also been גלות galus and that affects
the status and the קדושה kedusha of the land. But in theory
you could imagine a time, I don't know, how about pre-בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, when they walked in from the time of יהושע? Yehoshua?
You could imagine a time when you have שמיטה דאורייתא shmita de'oraisa
without a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So it's not exactly, we shouldn't
just sort of easily accept this idea that שביעית shevi'is is related
to מקדש. Mikdash. שביעית Shevi'is more logically is related to the land
and being settled in the land and having dominion over the land.
But the idea that it should be connected to מקדש Mikdash is
not at all obvious. But anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
And therefore, רבן גמליאל ובית דינו Rabban Gamliel ve-veis dino were able
to reject it because they felt that was only in the time
of the מקדש, Mikdash, there's no מקדש Mikdash now, so we can
do away with it. So the גמרא's Gemara shifting from saying there
are two components, a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha lemoshe misinai דאורייתא de'oraisa
and a דרבנן, derabbanan, and רבן גמליאל ובית דינו Rabban Gamliel ve-veis
dino only got rid of the דרבנן, derabbanan, it now seems, the
גמרא Gemara didn't say it explicitly but it pretty much seems, that
the גמרא's Gemara now understanding that the whole period, all the way
back to פסח Pesach or שבועות. Shavuot. whatever you think is the
proper time, maybe the rabbis had the latitude of figuring out exactly
when it began, but nevertheless, the whole period is either biblical or
הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha l'moshe misinai, and nevertheless comes along רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel and בית דין Beis din and they get rid of
it. How do they get rid of it? Because they say we
don't think it's really biblical, we only think it's הלכה למשה מסיני
Halacha l'moshe misinai and we believe that the הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
l'moshe misinai does not apply nowadays, and therefore get rid of the
whole thing. So those are just very different bits and approaches to
this idea of תוספת, Tosafet, and again I want to remind you
that the first thing the גמרא Gemara said before that, which I
found very compelling, was maybe the reason they reject it was because
of the comparison to שבת Shabbat and thinking about the issue of
the שמיטה Shmita שבת Shabbat type of a comparison. And also what
the גמרא Gemara says is even if it is biblical or הלכה
למשה מסיני Halacha l'moshe misinai you don't get lashes because, and this
gets to the whole idea of תוספת, Tosafet, you know, is תוספת
Tosafet just a מצוה Mitzvah to do a תוספת Tosafet or is
it a real extension of the קדושה Kedusha and of the status
into the previous period? And if it's a real extension of the
קדושה Kedusha to the previous period, well maybe you'll get lashes because
now it turns out that we're in שמיטה, Shmita, you know, we're
in a period that has קדושת שמיטה. Kedushat Shmita. And the answer
is maybe that even if it is that idea, it doesn't carry
the full weight. And as I mentioned to you, that gets to
the interesting idea of תוספת שבת. Tosafet Shabbat. Nobody for example says
you get lashes, you know, or worse if you violated תוספת שבת,
Tosafet Shabbat, but that doesn't mean that we can't think of it
that there's some קדושה Kedusha in the previous period because there is
a discussion of whether you can do the מצוות Mitzvos of the
day, where you can be מקיים Mekayem them during the period of
תוספת. Tosafet. You finished your סעודת שבת Seudat Shabbat before it got
dark. You sat in your סוכה Sukkah before it got dark, you
know, would you be מקיים Mekayem the
מצוה Mitzvah of the יום, Yom, you know, during the period of
תוספת Tosafet is an interesting debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Nobody says
it by מצה Matzah because by מצה Matzah there's particularly an idea
of לילה. Layla. בערב תאכלו מצות Ba'erev tochlu matzos or eating the
meat, you know, it's the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach says בלילה הזה
Balayla hazeh so therefore, you know, so anyway but it is discussed
by other by the other חגים. Chagim. Yes.
To clarify. You said תוספת שבת Tosafet Shabbat doesn't mean like let's
say I was מקבל שבת Mekabel Shabbat at like פלג Plag or
something that I'm not getting lashes by like go and light my
candle. I do mean that.
What do you mean?
No, that's not meaning, so if I do שבת Shabbat early. Yes
we are.
Sure we are. That's why תוספת שבת.
Tosafet Shabbat. So if I go and דאוון מנחה Daven Mincha at
RJC, you know, then שבת Shabbat for me because I did
קבלת שבת Kabbalat Shabbat and מעריב. Maariv. Right. You're not allowed to
turn on the light.
Right. So so I would be if I violated that,
it's סקילה, Sekila, right?
No! Absolutely really? That's what you thought? Absolutely not. Absolutely not. No,
the period of תוספת שבת Tosafet Shabbat does not have the weight
of the...
So even though I מקבל שבת...
Mekabel Shabbat... Exactly.
So I'm not allowed to, but if I did it, if I
violated it, it would be no...
Right. Correct. Now, does that mean because it's not there's no קדושת
שבת Kedushat Shabbat at all, it's just this thing you're doing called
תוספת? Tosafet? Or no, maybe as you intuitively understood, you are bringing
שבת Shabbat early, but it's not real שבת, Shabbat, it's תוספת שבת.
Tosafet Shabbat. You brought the קדושה Kedusha with if you want to
say conceptually, it's קדושת שבת Kedushat Shabbat without it being the יום
שבת. Yom Shabbat. So anyway, but or the קדושה Kedusha maybe doesn't
have the full weight of the קדושה. Kedusha. You certainly do not
get the punishment, there's a question about which which is what why
you don't get the lashes for שביעית. Shevi'it. This question of whether
you get certain קיומין. Kiyumin. Okay, so let's take a look now
as the גמרא Gemara continues. אבל
לא ממי גשמים וממי הקילון. Aval lo mimei geshamim umimei hakilon. Now,
you cannot so we got through the basic things of why there
can be override, חול המועד Chol Hamoed sounds like it's דרבנן D'rabanan
and טרחא, Tircha, though that's going to be revisited, שמיטה Shmita nowadays
or certain things are דרבנן, D'rabanan, and now we get to the
fact that it can only be א במקום הפסד Aleph b'makom hefsed
and ב Beis when it is what do you call it, when
it is about not going to be an undue טרחא. Tircha. So
you can use the water from a spring, but you cannot use
rainwater, collected rainwater like in a barrel, or a קילון. Kilon. A
קילון Kilon is some type of a bucket system which requires a
lot of effort of raising up, you know, water from a like
a from a ditch or from a, you know, from a well.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to say, ask what's the big deal
of rainwater? If you got rainwater in a bucket, why is that
such a problem? Where's the big effort there? Right? So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא מי קילון
Bishlama mei kilon I get the water the problem about the water
from this like a, you know, well and the bucket system,
איכא טרחא יתירה ika tircha yeseira that's a lot of effort. אלא
מי גשמים מאי טרחא איכא? Ela mei geshamim mai tircha ika? What
type of effort is it if you got water collected in a
barrel, rainwater? אמר רבי אילא אמר רבי יוחנן גזירה מי גשמים אטו
מי קילון. Amar Rabbi Ila amar Rabbi Yochanan gezeira mei geshamim atu
mei kilon.
No, if we let you use מי גשמים mei geshamim you'll come
to use מי קילון. mei kilon. Now what's the comparison? Comparison is
it's collected water. As opposed to a spring which is running and
flowing water, this is collected water. So if we tell you you
can draw water from your rainwater in a barrel, you'll say well
what difference is it drawing water from a rainwater in a barrel
and drawing water from the water at the bottom of my well?
Right? And then you're going to go and you're going to שלעפ
shlep the water from the bottom of the well and that is
טרחא יתירה. tircha yeseira. So that's why we're not going to allow
it. By the way, some wells actually are springs, are are from
fed from underground springs, others are collected water and the problem here,
if it's like deep down in the well, is not like by
הלכות. hilchos. the water came from, but anyway that's why it describes
it not as מי בורות mei boros but מי קילון, mei kilon,
water of the קילון kilon which is this system of raising the
water. Okay, so anyway, but you'll make that comparison, collected water in
a barrel, collected water in a well, what's the difference? So therefore
we can't allow you to do even the rain water. So the
גמרא Gemara says רב אשי אמר מי גשמים גופייהו לידי מי קילון
אתו. Rav Ashi amar mei geshomim gufayhu liydei mei kilon asu. Rain
water itself, not just will lead to a different case of the
well water, rain water itself will become a case of a bucket
of of having to raise it with a bucket and a barrel.
Why? Because maybe you've got your rain water collected in a huge
barrel, right? You ever see those the big things they've got, oh
is that rain water when they water towers? What is that? Is
that rain water? Okay, anyway, you could have your collected rain water
in a big barrel and you know, how am I going to
go down to the bottom of the barrel if there's only a
little bit left? I would have to do some type of a
שלעפפינג schlepping you know, whatever, again, it's hard for me to imagine
how much effort it takes to get water from the bottom of
a barrel, but anyway, so it's not just it'll lead to a
different case. The rain water case itself sometimes is scenarios that there
will be an amount a good amount of טירחא tircha involved when
it gets low and therefore we can't allow that either. Okay, דקא
מיפלגי בדדרבי זירא dikamiflagi bid'Rabbi Zeira and their debate plays itself out
in a statement of
רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. דאמר רבי זירא אמר רבה בר ירמיה אמר
שמואל נהרות המושכין מים מן האגמים מותר להשקות מהן בחולו של מועד.
d'amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rabbah bar Yirmeyah amar Shmuel neharos hamoshchin mayim
min ha'agamim mutar lehashkos mehen b'cholo shel moed. If you have a
a river that is and that is, you know, drawing water or
from a from a swamp, from like a pond, you can use
that to water your field on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So, what's
the scenario? The scenario is that you've got basically you've got your
אגם, agam, you've got your, not the painter, you've got you've got
your swamp, okay? That's like מי גשמים. mei geshomim. That's collected water,
that's not flowing water, right? And then, you know, but it's a
huge body of water, right? It's big, it's collected but it's big.
And you've got like some type of a thing in the אגם
agam water is running down through this sort of, you know, you
know, ואדי wadi or river, whatever, and here's your field and you're
going to draw water from that field, okay, and to water it.
So you could say well isn't that just like a case of
rain water because it's ultimately coming from collected water? The answer is
yeah, it's coming from collected water but you never, a, there's no
effort, it's flowing and it's running right by your field, it's not
like you have to go down deep and b, there's never a
concern that that swamp and that pond is going to is going
to be empty. It's not like a finite, I mean it is
finite but you know, it's not like a certain amount of water
collected in a barrel. Okay, so let's take a look.
So wait, wait, wait, so that's a spring, that's like flowing water.
You don't have to you don't have to draw...
Well, you might no you do probably have to draw it and
bring it to your field, it's not like your field it's not
like there's no, you know, it's not like you got an irrigation
system and sprinklers going on but you don't have to like whatever
it is, it's not like a lot of טירחא tircha of raising
it up, it's just more conveying it horizontally rather than vertically. That's
my understanding of it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מר אית
ליה דרבי זירא ומר לית ליה דרבי זירא. mar is lei d'Rabbi
Zeira u'mar leis lei d'Rabbi Zeira. One would hold of him, one
would not. What does it mean? The one that says it's concerned
that any time it's collected water that will lead to a case
of מי קילון mei kilon meaning that'll that you know, that'll then
you'll come do a different case of מי קילון mei kilon and
what do I care how much water you've got and how convenient
and wonderful this is? Fundamentally it's based on collected water and if
we let you do this next time you'll be doing מי קילון.
mei kilon. Where if the concern is that this case itself will
turn into the need for the קילון, kilon, the need for using
this, you know, this sort of water drawing system, so this case
will never turn into it. You've got a huge pond, a huge
swamp and whatever and this is never going to turn into a
case of מי קילון. mei kilon. And therefore this would not be
a problem. Okay, so that's the issue of the rain water case
which is is the rain water because it'll turn into a case
of מי קילון mei kilon and therefore in cases where that wouldn't
happen it would be allowed, or is the rain water problem because
it would lead to different scenarios of מי קילון mei kilon and
therefore it will always be forbidden because if you do this it
would lead to you next time doing something else. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. גופא, gufa, let's take a look
at that statement of רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. אמר רבי זירא אמר
רבה בר ירמיה אמר שמואל נהרות המושכין מים מן האגמים amar Rabbi
Zeira amar Rabbah bar Yirmeyah amar Shmuel neharos hamoshchin mayim min ha'agamim
if you have these rivers or ואדיס wadis that draw water from
the swamps, מותר להשקות מהן בחולו של מועד, mutar lehashkos mehen b'cholo
shel moed,
you are allowed you are allowed to to water from them on
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. איתיביה רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא eiseivei Rabbi Yirmeyah
l'Rabbi Zeira so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah challenged רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
אבל לא ממי גשמים ולא ממי קילון. aval lo mimei geshomim v'lo
mimei kilon.
You cannot water from, you know, rain water and מי קילון mei
kilon and he said isn't this I mean it's just unpacking what
we said before, isn't this essentially מי גשמים? mei geshomim? It's collected
water.
So I've, you know, you could understand the question that's type of
מי גשמים. mei geshomim. I think רש"י Rashi reads it, hold on,
let me just check the רש"י. Rashi.
Right, okay, that's basically
right. Isn't this a type of a case of collected rainwater? And
maybe he even saw it as we'll see from the answer that
maybe even the אגם Agam will go dry and therefore it will
come to having to use to have to use
the the this the like the water drawing system. Why are you
assuming this won't be just like a normal case of collecting water?
So isn't that what it is, collected water? So אמר ליה, Amar
Lei, he said to him ירמיה ברי, Yirmiyah Beri, ירמיה Yirmiyah my
son, I think he named that affectionately, not that he was really
his son. הני אגמי דבבל כמיא דלא פסקי דמו. Hani Agamei De'vavel
Ke'maya De'la Paski Damu. No, the swamps in בבל, Bavel, we're always
hearing how בבל Bavel is such a wetland, the swamps in בבל
Bavel are so big and deep and whatever, the water's never going
to run out. Did he stay in בבל? Bavel? What? He's well
he's living in בבל. Bavel.
So but you're right, now we find out that this would be
true only in בבל. Bavel. So again, why would this be allowed?
It would be allowed because the only problem of using collected water
is because it might run out or it might get very low
and you'll have to therefore do this whole drawing and raising up
of the water and therefore in this type of a case in
בבל Bavel with the swamp and whatever it'll never lead to the
case of the water getting too low and therefore you don't have
to worry. Like the גמרא Gemara said before, the only concern about
these cases is when it might itself become a case where the
water level is too low. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, הפסוקות והבריכות, Ha'pesukot Ve'ha'berichot, this is
also collected pools of water, different types of constructions of them, but
collected pools of water שנתמלאו מים מערב יום טוב, She'nitmal'u Mayim Me'erev
Yom Tov, and they were filled, rained ערב יום טוב, Erev Yom
Tov, so now they're filled with water. This is like a מי
גשמים Mei Geshamim case. אסור להשקות מהן בחול המועד. Assur Le'hashkot Me'hen
Be'chol Ha'moed. You cannot fill from them on חול המועד. Chol Ha'moed.
ואם
הייתה אמת המים עוברת ביניהם מותר. Ve'im Hayeta Amat Ha'mayim Overet Beineichem
Mutar. Now let's say however you had a what do you call
it, a channel, right, a not channel, what's it called, something,
a water channel, a
water channel, right, okay, anyway, you had a water channel that passes
from them between them, then it's permissible. Why?
Because basically that's a case of... well let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so מותר. Mutar. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, where are we? אמר רב פפא והוא שרובה
של אותה שדה שותה מאותה אמת המים. Amar Rav Pappa Ve'hu She'rubah
Shel Otah Sadeh Shoteh Me'otah Amat Ha'mayim. So basically what you've got
is you've
got... let me just reread רש"י Rashi make sure I got this
case right.
Right, okay, so basically what you got here is you got this
water, you got this well that's filled with water, right? And then
you got a water channel that's and that's filled up from rainwater
before שבת, Shabbat, okay? And then you've got a water channel that's
coming at the bottom or somehow whatever, you've got a water channel
that brings it and it's now right by your and it's right
by your field, okay? So what you can do is you can
go ahead and you can draw the water from this channel and
irrigate your field. Why? Why aren't you concerned that this water itself,
this rainwater here, right, will get low and then in order to
get the rainwater you're going to have to do the whole raising
it up and that'll be the extra effort? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, we're talking that the water that's already in the channel
is enough or the majority of your field can be watered with
it. So therefore even if this, the water level goes low, we're
not afraid you're going to have to come here and start raising
up the water because you've got enough water already immediately available in
this channel to take care of the needs of your field. All
right, so that's why we're not afraid that it'll lead to a
case where you're going to have to go to this effort. Yes?
You think he's following the spring-fed channel which is constantly replenishing
itself?
A spring-fed? Spring-fed. Spring-fed.
Well
רש"י Rashi says, that might be how the English is understanding רש"י.
Rashi.
רש"י Rashi does not say that. So you could be right. רש"י
Rashi does not say that. רש"י Rashi just says you'll be able
to sustain your field by the water of the אמה. Amah. So
the English must be understanding that what he means by it, are
you reading an English explanation of רש"י? Rashi? Because I'm not seeing
anything in רש"י Rashi that says that. So רש"י Rashi says, what
all רש"י Rashi says that I'm reading is that even if this
dries up, you can sustain your field based on the אמה, Amah,
okay? What?
רש"י. Rashi. Yeah, anyway what רש"י Rashi says is even if this
dries up we don't have to be afraid because you can sustain
it based on the אמה. Amah. So I'm understanding that the אמה
Amah is not its own water source. Right, you could have understood
there's different, there's this, there's two things... things going on, there's the
בריכות breichot and then there's something else, which is an אמה. amah.
So it's telling you, oh, you can use this because even if
this dries up, this separate water source will be sufficient, and this
is spring-fed. That seems to be how the Ringleish is reading רש"י,
Rashi, which might very well be correct. I was understanding that the
אמה amah is made to convey water, and therefore, and the point
is, is that even if this dries up, you're okay because there's
already enough water in the אמה. amah. But one way or another,
the point is you can use this water because even if it
dries up, you won't come to be drawing the water from the
bottom of it. The אמה amah has the water that it's providing
for the field. Okay, so let's take a look. It says like
this: אמר פפא והוא שרובו של אותה שדה שותה מאותה אמת המים.
Amar Pappa ve-hu she-rubo shel osah sadeh shoseh me-osah amas hamayim.
That's if the majority of the field can be watered from that
אמה, amah, therefore you don't have to worry that the בריכה breichah
will dry up, because even if so, you're covered. רב אשי אמר
אפילו אם אין רובו של אותה שדה, Rav Ashi amar afilu im
ein rubo shel osah sadeh, even if it's not the majority of
the field, שותה כיון דקמתחא ואתיא, shoseh keivan de-kamatchi ve-atya, since the
water is constantly flowing and coming through that אמה, amah, מימר אמר
אי לא שתיא לחד יומא תשתייא לתרי ותלתא יומי. memar amar ilo
shatya le-chad yoma tishatya le-trei ve-tlasa yomei.
You're not going to go ahead and still have to go and
oh my god now I'm going to have to go draw water
from the bottom of the well or whatever. No, if you've got
an aqueduct that brings water straight to your field and it's constantly
flowing, then even if today I've used up today's supply of water,
I'm not going to start שלעפנינג schlepping somewhere to, you know, go
raising water, because tomorrow there'll be more water flowing in my aqueduct
and therefore I'm going to be getting it tomorrow. So even if
it might dry up today, we're not concerned it'll lead to drawing
water because you'll be because because you're in a situation where you're
going to rely on tomorrow's. It'll rain
again. Do you understand? Yeah. Or maybe it comes from a spring.
Or maybe an אמה, amah, maybe what Jonathan says is correct, if
it's coming from a spring, that would certainly explain it. Okay, but
whatever it is, this אמה amah is providing you with water and
therefore you are you can rely confidently enough on this, either psychologically
or in reality, that you don't have to worry that this is
going to dry up. Okay, so now we continue. מימר, Memar, okay,
where were we? תנו רבנן בריכה שנוטפת מים משדה בית השלחין זו
מותר להשקות ממנה שדה בית השלחין אחרת. Tanu rabanan breichah she-notefes mayim
mi-sadeh beis hashalachin zo mutar le-hashkos mimenu sadeh beis hashalachin acheres.
If you've got a well that is dripping water from one בית
השלחין beis hashalachin into the next, you can use you can use
that water for the other בית השלחין. beis hashalachin. So now what
does that mean? What's the case? So רש"י Rashi basically says like
this: that
that
what you have here is
you've got two fields. One is higher than the other, okay? Here's
your field number one, and here's your field number
two. Okay, somewhere on some mountain or whatever. Here's your well-spring, okay?
Here's your live water. So you're very happy in field number one
because you can go ahead and take this live well and you
can water your field. Now what happens is, because it's all on
a mountain and on an angle, some of the runoff from field
number one collects in a in a בריכה, breichah, in some type
of a of a of a puddle, or whatever whatever, you know,
a of a pool. Thank you. Here between field number one and
number two. If you're in field number two, you can use water
from this בריכה. breichah. Why? It's collected water. Yeah, it's collected water,
but it's collected water that comes from the live source here that
is dripping, dripping, dripping, and feeding into it. So in a way,
it's collected water that's regularly being replenished from a live source and
therefore it's allowed. Now, that doesn't mean really your problems are always
solved. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. So והא עבידא דתסקא, ve-ha avidah de-taska, one minute, I
mean, you're only getting little drips from the top field, sometimes that
pool will empty out, you know, and and you're going to have
to come and draw water. So אמר רבי ירמיה ועדיין היא מנטפת.
Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah ve-adayin hi metaftafas. No, we're allowing you to draw
water only as the dripping is continuing to go right now into
the pond, into the pool. Okay, now again, that doesn't mean it
won't dry up, because how quick is the rate of the dripping?
But anyway, that's the scenario. אמר אביי והוא שלא פסק מעיין ראשון.
Amar Abaye ve-hu she-lo pasak ma'ayan rishon. And that's also only in
the case where the that the that this well-spring, you know, is
also still continuing to provide. Not only is it continuing to drip
in here, but this is continuing to provide water into the first
into the first one. And therefore, it's like it's all an extension,
the way I would sort of frame it in a more formal
term, is that it's like it's all an extension of the well-spring.
And therefore, it's not drawing from collected water, it's drawing from the
well-spring, you know, or you could try to just say, the reality
is it won't dry up, but I think what we're more doing
is framing it as an extension of the well-spring. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, let me just see one thing.
Right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנא, Tana,
we taught in a ברייתא, beraisa, רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר שתי
ערוגות. Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer shetei arugos.
So if you have
two beds like let's say vegetable gardens one higher than another לא
ידלה מן הראשונה וישקה את התחתונה lo yidleh min harishonah veyashkeh et
hatachtonah וישקה את העליונה. veyashkeh et haelyonah.
So do not be דולה doleh do not draw well term that
now as draw water from the bottom one in order to water
the top one. Okay cause again that would be like drawing water
from a case below to feed a case on top presumably even
if below maybe is a type of a wellspring or something okay
but still that's considered to be too much טרחא. tircha. אמר יתר
כן אמר רבי
אליעזר בר שמעון Amar yeter ken amar Rabbi Eliezer bar Shimon אפילו
ערוגה אחת חציה נמוך וחציה גבוה. afilu arugah achat chetzyah namuch vechetzyah
gavoah. Let's say you have one bed of vegetables and part of
it is on the low lands and parts on the highlands but
it's all essentially the same continuous planting. לא ידלה ממקום נמוך וישקה
למקום גבוה. lo yidleh mimakom namuch veyashkeh lemakom gavoah. Again do not
draw water from the low place in order to water the high
place. So there's this big thing like I said about the vertical
drawing of water. Like the horizontal conveyance is not such an issue
but drawing going down low and drawing up is considered is considered
an issue. Again what I don't really know is when he says
don't be דולה doleh can I like take the water here and
walk up the hill? Is that being דולה doleh or is דולה
doleh only like lowering some type of a thing down and drawing
some type of a thing up? It would seem to me that
while the second case is more clearly the דולה doleh drawing up
water that that probably is less effort than filling it up and
then walking up with the bucket. So I gotta tell you I'm
not a farmer I really can't help you too much here. Okay
let's keep on going. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan we taught מדלין לירקות
כדי לאוכלן. madlin liyerakot kedei lochlan.
You can be דולה doleh for vegetables in order to eat them
ואם בשביל ליפותן אסור veim bishvil liyapotan asur but if it's to
make them better it's forbidden. Now that what it sounds like is
this case of הפסד hefsed right? You can be דולה doleh for
vegetables this drawing which generally we prohibit if it's in order to
make sure that they're edible that they don't like rot or something
but if it's just to make them better it's forbidden. Okay which
is interesting because normally we assume that a heavy טרחא tircha would
always be forbidden okay and here we're saying it would
be you want to
eat I understand I don't know fully what it means. Okay but
go with it. Anyway that's what we said. But here it seems
like הפסד hefsed is an allowance even though until now we've been
saying that too much טרחא tircha doesn't allow isn't allowed even במקום
הפסד. bemakom hefsed. But let's tell now look at a story and
see how this gets re-understood. רבינא ורבה תוספאה הוו קאזלי באורחא Ravina
veraba tosfah havu kaazli beorcha
Ravina and Rabba Tosfah that was his name were going on the
way. חזיוה לההוא גברא דהוה דלי דבלא בחולא דמועדא. chazyuh lehahu gavra
dehavah dali divla bechola demoada. They saw a person that was drawing
water like drawing with a bucket raising up water on חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. Exactly what our משנה mishna prohibits. אמר ליה רבה תוספאה
לרבינא Amar leh Rabba Tosfah leRavina Rabba Tosfah said to Ravina ליתי
מר לשמתיה? leiti mar leshamteih? Why doesn't the master go and put
him in חרם cherem put him in נידוי nidui at least voice
some sense of being of objection and that what he's doing is
wrong? אמר ליה Amar leh why should I? והתניא vehatanya we taught
in a ברייתא braitah מדלין לירקות כדי לאוכלן. madlin liyerakot kedei lochlan.
You can draw water for vegetables the case was it was a
vegetable garden and he's drawing water fine but maybe it's in order
to preserve the vegetables. אמר ליה Amar leh he said back to
him מי סברת מאי מדלין מדלין מיא? mi savrat mai madlin madlin
maya? Wait a minute. You think that when it says דולה doleh
there it means to draw water? That's not what that ברייתא braitah
means. You wouldn't you're not allowed to draw water even even to
preserve it like we said that's too much טרחא tircha טרחא tircha
is not allowed even במקום הפסד. bemakom hefsed. So if that's true
what does it mean to be דולה? doleh?
I'll tell you what it means.
מאי מדלין mai madlin know what it means to be מדלה madleh
שלופי shalufi it means to remove remove some of the vegetables to
let the other vegetables grow better. כדתנן kedetnan and look I'll give
you a משנה mishna uses that term it's not like a kvetch.
This is the terminology of the משנה. mishna. המדו בגפנים Hamadu bagefanim
if somebody is thinning out the vines in order to let the
other vines grow better. So כשם שהוא מדו בשלו כך הוא מדו
בשל עניים. keshem shehu madu beshelo kach hu madu beshel aniyim. The
same way you're thinning out your vines to encourage their growth if
there's a section that belongs to the poor because let's say it's
פאה peah or פרט peret or עוללות olelot some of the gifts
to the poor that you're leaving in your field but what you're
doing is you're doing this to increase the growth. So you also
can do it for the poor you can't say oh that's the
poor's part I can't touch it. No you're allowed to do it
to increase the growth. דברי רבי יהודה Divrei Rabbi Yehudah that's Rabbi
Yehuda said. רבי מאיר אומר בשלו הוא רשאי ואינו רשאי בשל עניים.
Rabbi Meir omer beshelo hu rashai veino rashai beshel aniyim. That discretion
you can have in yours you can't do it for the עניים.
aniyim. But okay that's a fascinating debate but what we see is
the word מדו madu means to thin out. So what he's saying
is when it says you can be מדו madu when it's for
the sake of preserving them but not just for the sake of
making them stronger it means the pulling out of vegetables to let
the other vegetables continue to grow in a healthy way. That's allowed
on חול המועד Chol HaMoed but not drawing water. Drawing water is
אסור asur even במקום הפסד. bemakom hefsed. אמר ליה Amar leh he
said back to him one minute. והתניא מדלין מים לירקות כדי לאוכלן?
vehatanya madlin mayim liyerakot kedei lochlan? I have a ברייתא braitah that
doesn't just say מדלין לירקות madlin liyerakot which could mean you thin
out the vegetables. It says you can be דולה doleh water for
the vegetables which clearly means draw water. אמר ליה אי תניא תניא.
Amar leh i tanya tanya. Oh if you've got a ברייתא braitah
you've got a ברייתא. braitah. Okay so okay. I guess I was
wrong. So anyway, so here we have an interesting question, right? We
have all this stuff again, I really can't get my head around
why it's so terrible to draw water and why it's so much
less of a טרחה tircha to walk water than to draw water,
but whatever it is, drawing water is a big concern and even
other things are prohibited you might lead to the drawing water, even
במקום הפסד, bemakom hefseid, but we do have at least this ברייתא
beraisa at the end based on this last read of this ברייתא
beraisa that would say that sometimes במקום הפסד bemakom hefseid it would
be allowed like this case of the vegetables, but maybe vegetables needed
less water so it wasn't as much טרחה, tircha, I don't really
know the full parameters. Okay, now we move on. ואין עושים עוגיות
לגפנים. Ve'ein osim ugiyot lagefanim. You cannot make circle furrows to collect
water around the vine. So מאי עוגיות, Mai ugiyot, what are these
עוגיות? ugiyot? אמר רב יהודה בנקי. Amar Rav Yehuda banki. They're בנקי.
banki. Okay, which is these circular furrows. תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami
hachi similar: אלו
הן עוגיות, Eilu hen ugiyot, these are the עוגיות, ugiyot, בדידין שבעיקרי
זיתים, bedidin shebe'ikrei zeitim, again, somehow these words all mean essentially the
same thing, these furrows by the roots of the olive trees, ושבעיקרי
גפנים veshebe'ikrei gefanim and by the roots of the vines that collect
water. איני? Eini? Is that really true? והא רב יהודה שרא לבני
בר ציתא? Veha Rav Yehuda shara livnei Bar Tzaita? Rav Yehuda allowed
the people of this place of בר ציתא Bar Tzaita למיבר בנקי
לכרמיהון lemivar banki lecharmeihon to
make these furrows to collect water for their vineyards and here's saying
you can't do it on חול המועד chol hamoed and he allowed
it on חול המועד. chol hamoed. So the גמרא gemara says, לא
קשיא הא בחדתי הא בעתיקי. Lo kashya ha bchadti ha be'atiki. It's
not a problem. I was talking about old, or excuse me, old
furrows or new ones. If they're old ones, so then you're just
like fixing them. And as we see later in the משנה, mishna,
it's not as much effort and maybe also there because it's not
so much like this whole new project, we're more lenient when it
comes to fixing them. So if they sort of collapsed a little,
that would be okay. But a new one, to dig a new
one from scratch, that's forbidden.
Okay. So now the גמרא, gemara, so that's another qualification on the
משנה. mishna. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer,
back to the
משנה, mishna, אין עושים את האמה. ein osim es ha'amma. He says
you cannot make a אמה, amma, this canal, on שביעית shevi'it or
on חול המועד. chol hamoed. And the rabbis said that, what does
he say? You can't dig a canal on שביעית shevi'it and חול
המועד. chol hamoed. And the rabbis said that עושים אמה בתחילה בשביעית,
osim amma batchila beshevi'it, you can dig it initially on שביעית, shevi'it,
ומתקנים את המקולקלות umetaknim es hamikolkalos and you can fix the ones
that have collapsed and that have become damaged on חול המועד. chol
hamoed. So again, more lenient when something is fixing what's damaged than
when it's making it from scratch. So we have to understand the
rabbis, but first let's understand רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he says both
cases are forbidden. So let's see what the גמרא gemara says about
this, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya, I should say.
So it says בשלמא מועד משום טרחה. Bishlama moed mishum tircha. Again,
notice how the גמרא gemara is very consistently characterizing the nature of
מלאכה melacha on חול המועד, chol hamoed, טרחה, tircha, right? Rabbinic, טרחה
tircha and so on. So I get by חול המועד, chol hamoed,
you don't want to be digging ditches on חול המועד. chol hamoed.
What could be more backbreaking labor than digging ditches? It's a טרחה,
tircha, that I get. אלא
שביעית מאי טעמא? Ella shevi'it mai ta'ama? Why can't you dig a
ditch on שביעית? shevi'it? Now, you're not actually working the field, maybe
the water is being transported not to irrigate the field, but for
drinking water or for water to do my laundry in, right? Nobody
is saying you're irrigating the field, you're just digging a ditch and
a canal to convey the water. So why isn't that allowed on
שביעית? shevi'it? Very good question. פליגי בה רבי זירא ורבי אבא בר
ממל. Pligi bah Rabbi Zeira veRabbi Abba bar Mammel. It's a debate
of רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira and רבי אבא בר ממל. Rabbi Abba
bar Mammel. חד אמר מפני שנראה כעודר. Chad amar mipnei shenireh ke'oder.
One says, you know why? Because when you're digging in the dirt
and you're digging a ditch, it looks to other people like you
are doing the digging of the dirt, the loosening of the dirt,
that's not to plant, עודר oder is what you do like under
the tree or by the vine, but
to allow it to grow better. So you look like you're doing
עבודת קרקע. avodas karka. I know, that's the funny thing, right? And
there's no tree anywhere around, I know. וחד אמר מפני שמכשיר אגפיה
לזריעה. Vechad amar mipnei shemachshir agapeha lezri'ah. The other one says because
when you dig out a ditch and you put little mounds of
dirt by the side of the ditch as you're digging it out,
so and then especially if water then is going to go through
the ditch and it's going to moisten it, so that ground that
you've now created at the banks is now very, fertile, and not
fertile, but whatever, very appropriate for planting. So therefore again, that's not
your intention, but you actually are creating a planting scenario. And that's
why, very much these rabbinic types of concerns. Well, that's why the
rabbis don't agree to it. Remember the rabbis said fine, the חכמים
chachamim say no problem digging ditches on
שביעית, shevi'it, digging these canals on שביעית. shevi'it. But we're trying to
understand why רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya has a
problem. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this:
מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? What would be a difference between their two
approaches? איכא בינייהו דקאתו מיא בתריה, Icha beinaihu deka'asu maya basrei, that
as soon as you finish digging, the water immediately starts flowing. So
מאן דאמר מפני שמכשיר אגפיה לזריעה, Man damar mipnei shemachshir agapeha lezri'ah,
if it's because the banks are now fit for planting, איכא, ika,
that's certainly an issue. right even more so because
the water is flowing. ומאן דאמר משום דנראה כעודר, Uman d'amar mishum
denireh keoder, but if the problem is that it looks at where
you're digging it's like you're helping things grow right there, ליכא. leika.
If the area that you're digging in is immediately being swamped, being
filled with water, it doesn't look like you're helping anything grow in
that area. ומשום הכי ולמאן דאמר משום דנראה כעודר לחוש נמי משום
דמשויה אגפיה לזריעה? Umeshum hachi uleman d'amar mishum denireh keoder lechush nami
mishum demashveya agapeya lizria? Why are these exclusive? If you've got the
problem that it looks like
you're being עודר, oder, you're doing something to help things grow, why
not also be concerned that you're making the ground fit for planting?
And therefore even in the case where the water flows immediately it
should also be a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know
what? You're right. That would be a problem. אלא, Ela, so everybody
would agree the problem that the ground becomes fit for planting according
to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria. איכא בינייהו, Ika
beinayhu, here's the difference: דקשקיל מיניה ושדי לבראי, dekashakil minei veshadi livrai,
that when you dig the ditch, the channel, you throw the dirt
far away. It doesn't you don't pile it up by the banks.
למאן דאמר משום דמשויה אגפיה לזריעה, Leman d'amar mishum demashveya agapeya lizria,
if it's because you're making the banks fit for planting, ליכא, leka,
you don't have loose dirt piling up by the banks, just throwing
the dirt far away. ולמאן דאמר משום דנראה כעודר, Uleman d'amar mishum
denireh keoder, but if the problem you in addition to making the
ground fit for planting, you also have the problem that it looks
like you're actually working the ground itself, איכא, ika, that is a
problem even if you throw the dirt far away. So the גמרא
Gemara is still not happy. ולמאן דאמר משום דמשויה אגפיה לזריעה לחוש
נמי משום דנראה כעודר? Uleman d'amar mishum demashveya agapeya lizria lechush nami
mishum denireh keoder? Why are they exclusive? You said the one that's
concerned about עודר oder is also concerned about the banks being fit
for planting. So say the other thing also. The one that's concerned
for the banks being fit for planting, let him also be concerned
that it looks like you're working the ground and in this case
also there should be an issue. So the גמרא Gemara says
עודר נמי, oder nami, no, that he even if he's concerned about
עודר oder the secondary concern, this is not so much of an
עודר oder scenario either. עודר נמי Oder nami כי קשקיל בדוכתיה מנח
ליה. ki kashakil beduchtiya manach lei. In a normal case of עודר
oder of working the ground, when you take the dirt up you
leave it in the place, you don't throw it away. So if
your primary concern is that you're making the banks fit for planting
and you also say, yeah, I realize that it also has a
problem that it looks like you're working the ground, this case you'd
let go because this case doesn't look so much like you're working
the ground. But if your primary concern was it looks like you're
working the ground, then this case you would also be concerned about.
All right. Whatever it is, those are the various reasons. אמימר מתני
לה משום דנראה כעודר. Amemar masni lah mishum denireh keoder. אמימר Amemar
explicitly teaches in the משנה Mishna that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaria forbids it or maybe at a ברייתא Braisa where
he explicitly said that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria
forbids it because it looks like
you're working the ground. So then וקשיא ליה vekasheya lei and then
he had a problem רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אדרבי אלעזר בן עזריה.
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria ad'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria is contradicting himself.
מי אמר רבי אלעזר בן עזריה כל שנראה כעודר אסור? Mi amar
Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria kol shenireh keoder assur? Did רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria really say anytime it looks like you're
working the ground it's forbidden on שביעית? Shevi'is? ורמינהו, Uraminhu, I'll ask
you on that. עושה אדם את זבלו אוצר. Oseh adam es zivlo
otzar. Can you take the, you know, even though it's שמיטה, Shmita,
your animals will still be excreting. So can you take their excrement
and you want to save up their excrement, right, because that is
good fertilizer. So can you take their excrement and pile it up
in your field or does piling up excrement in the field look
like you are fertilizing your field? So let's take a look at
how you would do it in a way that it would not
be a problem of looking like you're fertilizing your field. עושה אדם
את זבלו אוצר. Oseh adam es zivlo otzar. So you can the
first position is, yeah, put your the excrement in the field and
don't have to worry about it. That's fine on שמיטה Shmita because
you're just doing it to collect it. רבי מאיר אוסר. Rabbi Meir
osser. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has some requirement. And first, עד שיעמיק
שלושה טפחים, ad sheyaamik shlosha tfachim, you either have to dig a
hole three טפחים tfachim and put it in the hole. And therefore
it's clear that you're collecting it and that you're not fertilizing the
field. Maybe even if it goes higher than the ground level, but
once you start by putting it in a hole it's okay. או
עד שיגביה ג' טפחים o ad sheyagbeha gimmel tfachim or that you
have to have it go higher than three טפחים. tfachim. Also then
it's clear that you are have a big pile of
it and not that you are fertilizing your field. היה לו דבר
מועט, Haya lo davar muat, if however before שמיטה Shmita started you
already had a little pile of excrement there, then מוסיף עליו והולך.
mosif alav veholech. Then you can add to it, then clearly when
you're bringing out excrement people see you're replenishing the pile that you've
got and not that you're actually going ahead and fertilizing your field.
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria now אוסר עד שיעמיק
שלושה או עד שיגביה שלושה. osser ad sheyaamik shlosha o ad sheyagbeha
shlosha. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria similar to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's forbidden unless you put it in a
ditch, a you make a ditch three טפחים tfachim dig and put
it in, או עד שיגביה שלושה O ad sheyagbeha shlosha or you
put it higher than three טפחים tfachim או עד שיתן על הסלע
o ad sheyiten al hasela or that you put it on a
rock. Now,
anyway, all that is fascinating. What does it have to do with
us? Because if you're digging a ditch to put your the excrement
in, right, so you're digging a ditch in your field on שמיטה.
Shmita. So how could רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaria
have a say you're never allowed to dig a ditch in your
field on שמיטה? Shmita? Here you're digging a ditch in your field
on שמיטה. Shmita. So let's take a look. רבי אלעזר ורבי אבא
בר ממל, Rabbi Elazar ve'Rabbi Abba bar Memel,
two explanations. חד אמר כגון שהעמיק. Chad amar kegon shehe'emik. We're not
saying you dig a ditch now on שביעית, Shvi'is, on שמיטה, Shmitah,
and put the excrement in it. We're saying it already had the
ditch, but not that you would dig the ditch now. That you
wouldn't be allowed to do. ואידך אמר, Ve'idakh amar, the other says
a simpler answer, זיבלא מוכיח עליה. zivla mokhiah aleh. I think the
excrement makes it clear what you're doing. So if you're סתם stam
digging a ditch on שמיטה Shmitah in a field and or somewhere
it might look like you're working the land. But if you're digging
a ditch and you're in the process of moving a pile of
excrement in it or you've got all this excrement piled up, it's
clear what you're doing it for. Of course then you could say
well maybe the case of digging the ditch for the water channel,
there's to be enough context to make it clear. But maybe it's
not enough visual context. Here there's an immediate visual context and that
makes it all very clear. Okay, so we'll pick up here tomorrow.